[SPEAKER_02]: Well, there's nothing else I had thought about, something that I thought might be useful.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you often talk about enduring things on the right level.
[SPEAKER_02]: So... Well, first, what exactly needs to be endured?
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, what's the right level?
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, well, I suppose, yeah, why is it important?
[SPEAKER_02]: What does it result in?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what needs to be endured is basically the... any type of pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's always a degree of pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're not enduring some random abstract ideas or things that are not... with emotional weight is not felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's always... that's what's like the importance, like... all things converge on feelings, as we said.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's basically where you find what you need to endure, what you need to not act out of.
[SPEAKER_01]: And...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, so the types of pressure, you know, you can describe them in your own way, in a way, like whatever pressures you, but fundamentally they're going to fall into five categories, the categories of the five hindrances.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I don't want to just say, oh, you endure five hindrances, because people have read extensively about five hindrances, and then they'll just
[SPEAKER_01]: Slot what I said into that idea of, aha, five hindrances, right, this is how you deal with them.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's like, you find, you find your existence always within one of those.
[SPEAKER_01]: It always has to be pressured by something, unless you're, like, completely in first jhāna, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: There always has to be a degree of pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you see whether it's the pressure in regard to sensuality,
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether you are immovable in regard to that pressure, whether it's the pressure in regard to ill-will, irritation, sloth, laziness, indolence, whether it's in regard to doubt, there is always something where your feelings are converging on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either craving for more pleasure, craving for less pain, craving for less doubt, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that needs to be recognized as a thing, as a state of mind, as a fundamental direction that you are in.
[SPEAKER_01]: What does it mean to endure it on the right level?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it means basically to see it to its extent as phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: To see it as a thing there, as we spoke before, independent of space or time or your actions that come out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just there on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: And to that extent it has arisen, and to that extent it's manifested, and you need to kind of... See, like, people might recognize sensual desire in their mind, or ill will,
[SPEAKER_01]: But they recognize it with all the, like, with a whole set of assumptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, this ill-will, it's in my brain, it's in my mind, it's the hormones, it's the electrons, it's the body, it's this, it's that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's your mode of existence at the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fully.
[SPEAKER_01]: Completely.
[SPEAKER_01]: As the entire picture.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is your basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind of ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind of lust.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind of doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to see it on the level of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, not as a thought in your head, like inside of this head that's part of this body, but pretty much recognize that whether it's the body, head, inside, out, all the notions of space are secondary to the enduring level of the pressure of certain feeling that you have at a time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it needs to be seen as a phenomenon independent of space and time, needs to be recognized in its own presence, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, obviously, the only way you can recognize that is if you have not been acting out of it habitually, which is already creating, furthering that division inside, outside, sense organs, sense objects, from here to there, in between the two, left and right.
[SPEAKER_01]: But all of that is within the enduring capsule of a certain hindrance.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you can't put a hindrance in front of you as an object of your experience, and you certainly can't measure it in space and time.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can certainly, you can, you can feel its pressure, you can feel its weight.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that abstract kind of recognition, seemingly abstract recognition, it's abstract because the mind is not trained in regard to it, but if you were to stop,
[SPEAKER_01]: And ask yourself, oh, is there a... like, are there even traces of sensuality, or is there a possibility of a non-arisen sensual desire to arise in me?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do I see that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, oh, if I... if I were to do this, this, and this, would sensuality arise?
[SPEAKER_01]: Recognizing that, that's a phenomenon real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: That possibility, that reality, that...
[SPEAKER_01]: That liability.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you need to see it enduring there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Regardless of what you do, where you look, where you sit, how you go, you need to see it independent of your movement, of your body, of your division in, out, mine, yours, world, science, everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what means you need to see this phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to recognize that it's real as such, in its own extent, wherever it has arisen, whichever way it has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't need to perceive it directly with your eyes, in order for it to be real.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just need to be aware of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you are aware of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you recognize also, anything I can be aware of, means it's real as such, within that level, within that domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, it's not real in the domain of sights, because I can't see it there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't exist there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's certainly real in the domain of thoughts, in the domain of images.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the domain of feeling, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's, as we spoke before, that's what yonis manasikāra is, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that would be the right level.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you start seeing the hindrances first, as the cornerstones that are kind of converging point, kind of the... we're trying to make you act, or you're trying to prolong pleasures, avoid pains.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if there is not an acute sensual desire present, as I said before,
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're still valuing sensuality, hoping it will come, hoping you'll get some more later on and so on, that is still operational within the hindrance of sensual desire, within that direction, within that pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the notion of pleasure, in that most kind of remote mental sense of an image of agreeability, is not seen real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not seen real as an image that directs your experience and then makes you crave for more.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's seen as a fleeting thought in regard to the more kind of real senses and even realer gratification that I get on account of sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: But all of that is known only because you have the thoughts there throughout that whole project of chasing sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, how would you know that touching something is pleasant before you touch it?
[SPEAKER_01]: How would you crave for it?
[SPEAKER_01]: How would you crave for its pleasure?
[SPEAKER_01]: Before you actually made the physical contact with, seemingly, where the pleasure comes from, which is the sense object.
[SPEAKER_01]: That would be inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, here you are acting, protecting, fighting, to gain, to get that sense of touch, sight, sound, smell, taste, touch, whatever it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Before you actually touch it, contact it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because pleasure is already rooted in your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's already, that image that exists, that defines everything else, yet you think it's just an abstract fleeting thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't, you don't recognize the, the, the weight of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And person wouldn't recognize it, because they would just be habitually acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as I said, through acting out of it, you are perpetuating that gratuitous, completely false division of, oh, this is inside, this is outside, that's real, this is not, not, not as real, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you start recognizing that, no, it's, hold on, it's real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, how do I know that this is pleasant before I even look at it?
[SPEAKER_01]: How do I know where to look for pleasure?
[SPEAKER_01]: If pleasure comes from the contact of the sense objects onto my sense organs, only time I can know it is while I'm being contacted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, here I am, planning, devising how to get it in the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you are equally gripped by that fever of sensual desire,
[SPEAKER_01]: In your thoughts, even before you actually touch the objects that you crave for.
[SPEAKER_01]: Quite often, after touching the objects or tasting the objects you crave for, it's like, it's a letdown.
[SPEAKER_01]: It wasn't as good as your thoughts were presenting the pleasure there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it needs to be seen real as such, on that level.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you stop gratuitously emphasizing the sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: But first, you need to be withdrawn from them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same with ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, like, you know, you might, you might have a hateful attitude towards sight, sound, smell, taste or touch, but fundamentally, that attitude precedes the actual contact with those hateful objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's already in your mind, mental framework.
[SPEAKER_01]: The disagreeability of it, the annoyance, the irritation.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you don't see that phenomenon real as such, enduring there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by overlooking it, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are under its pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all it takes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, look past the hindrance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't recognize it where it is, to the extent that it is, real as such, independent of space and time.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all it takes for it to hinder you, just to not see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're already under its influence.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the goal of that would be exactly that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Freedom from pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Freedom from five modes a pressure can assume.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, like, as you said, all of what you just said would be completely invisible if you're acting out of these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It does not exist.
[SPEAKER_02]: So then, it might be useful to...
[SPEAKER_02]: To clarify, what constitutes acting out?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it might be easy to assume that it's only kind of relatively coarse, as in, if I go and get the thing I want, and eat it, or, you know, see it, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, I suppose, I want, I don't know, to give an example.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you could even
[SPEAKER_02]: Somebody could listen to this, listen to what you're saying, and even just, I suppose, you know, a pressuring kind of thought comes up, and now you start trying to remember, or what did he say, and how do I... how did it... and that's already acting out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, see, first the course, the course acting out has to stop.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, precepts, sense restraint, it's just not negotiable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, dhamma does not exist.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is nowhere for dhamma to apply, unless that basis is developed beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's just... it's not up for debate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, acting out, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there will already be a hindrance of doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, where do I look?
[SPEAKER_01]: How do I see?
[SPEAKER_01]: How do I do that?
[SPEAKER_01]: And the skill there, inevitably, you're going to be... you're trying to deal without hindrance, you're going to get caught into another one, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you're going to get angry.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you're going to try to overcome that pain by craving for centrality, because that's your only means of escape, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's just too much, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the point is, that not to deal with an individual hindrance in that coarse manner, but to recognize...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you can initially, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if there is a hindrance of sensuality, well, don't go in the objects that would be making it worse.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you are completely just just sleepy and lazy, well, get off the comfortable couch.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't lay on it, because obviously it's gonna... it's just common sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that... it's nothing... it's not gonna uproot any hindrance.
[SPEAKER_01]: What would uproot them, eventually, is to recognize that whichever it is present, it's present through the pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, you might start by being gripped by the hindrance of doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, he said I must see this on the right level.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do I see this on the right level?
[SPEAKER_01]: And you recognize, hold on.
[SPEAKER_01]: My whole desire to see this on the right level, it's already coming out of a pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, that's what I need to do, not act out of the pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by recognizing the pressure, you won't act out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: By not acting out of it, you get to recognize it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, if the mind moves into, like, craving for sensual pleasure, again, oh, again, that's a pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't care what, what wants as its object.
[SPEAKER_01]: All I care is I'm pressured, I'm under its kind of weight, push in a certain direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I need to see.
[SPEAKER_01]: I need to see that pressure real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is pressure present.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like... And then, endure the pressure, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see, once you see through the hindrance, the pressure, its force, basically, where it kind of... where it has influence over you, the actual object and the content of the hindrance, you already surmount it.
[SPEAKER_01]: By recognizing the pressure of it, you're already not that much directed on central objects as you were before.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same with the doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, if you kind of overlook the pressure again, forget, try to get rid of it, you're gonna fall into the objects presented.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, doubt and figure out or sense objects or anger.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you actually recognize the pressure as as a necessary basis for any content of the hindrance, you are already uninvolved with the content.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're already closer to uprooting it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what I was going to say.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, like, if you recognize the... yeah, that pressure in any... in any way, for anything, you don't necessarily even need to, kind of, I don't know, classify it into...
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what I said.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can describe it in your own way.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, the Suttas describe it five hindrances, because that's all, but I'm sure not all the monks will necessarily see them back in the day.
[SPEAKER_01]: They had probably their own ways, but what they all had in common was the pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, where would...
[SPEAKER_01]: Where would you find that pressure?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, where would you find if there is a presence of pressure or possibility of the pressure increasing and so on?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where do you look for it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where is the level for that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you would know that if there is a feeling, to the degree that there is a feeling, to that degree there is a pressure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Any feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, pleasant feeling, that's a pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unpleasant feeling, that's a pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Neutral feeling, that's pressure, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pressure, then, when known, it's not unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: When not known, it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: But fundamentally, there is always a pressure for as long... Well, for as long as you're not an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, it's not always the same degree of pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: For somebody whose mind is free, partially free, and so on, he's obviously going to have less things pressuring him, because there are less fetters there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the point is, you need to recognize that, oh, it's not like, oh, I'm free from pressure now, and I'm not an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's always going to be a degree of feeling, to that extent, there is a degree of pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: To that extent, there is a potential for hindrance.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't see that pressure on the level that it exists,
[SPEAKER_01]: As a phenomenon, neither inside nor outside, neither in my head nor in the world, but here, real as such, I mean, the most real thing, directs your whole existence, shapes your whole life decisions and everything else, emotional needs and so on, and pressures.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't see it on that level, that's where it starts to hinder you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where its counterpart starts to hinder you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you see it as a pressure, it cannot.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's held, it's basically put in place.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's recognized for what it is,
[SPEAKER_01]: The beautiful, the ugly, the lack of energy, restlessness... Again, like, natural phenomenon in a way.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they don't need to... they hinder you when you are not developed in regard to their pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're developed in regard to their pressure, they cease to be hindrances.
[SPEAKER_01]: But those things that were hindering you, those contents, those objects, they do remain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, there's a sutta.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't remember the reference now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe I can...
[SPEAKER_01]: It describes exactly that.
[SPEAKER_01]: When rightly attended, they cease to be the hindrance, but they remain that which they were before.
[SPEAKER_01]: They hindered you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, obviously, you don't start unhindered.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't start by having a pure sign of beauty that then develops into sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mind not free from hindrances starts with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can only undo the degree of that sensuality and then discover that there is a pure sign of beauty, a pure sign of agreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, attended rightly, cannot bring lust to increase in you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Attended rightly to what?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, to that sign, to that pressure, to its characteristics and its core.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think, yeah, it's kind of about seeing what genuinely
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it's again...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you think you should do what you're supposed to do, you're not looking for the pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just acting out to get rid of the discomfort, which is exactly what hindrance wants you to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Indriyas doesn't care if you follow through and how far you go.
[SPEAKER_01]: As long as you act out of the pressure, that's all that matters.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're already caught, you're already hindered.
[SPEAKER_01]: How far you go and whether you get your gratification or not, that's all irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's only important to you because you're already caught.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you were to see that pressure as a phenomenon, like you were describing just now, correctly, there would not be... that pressure would not be felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you think you see it rightly as a phenomenon, but there is still that pressure, you are overlooking something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and that's the practice there, because initially, naturally, you emphasize your view.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where the views are kind of the most blameworthy thing, or the best thing that can free you.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, like, you have a criteria whereby, when the pressure is seen rightly, it ceases to pressure you, but it might not feel right to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you still emphasize that, oh, it doesn't feel right, I need to see it again until it feels right, that's already your view being put first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's already under the pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's where that kind of intelligence and understanding and discernment start to sort of play the part, where you recognize, okay,
[SPEAKER_01]: I know what's right, though.
[SPEAKER_01]: I understood that rightly seeing pressure means not being pressured, there and then, while the pressure remains.
[SPEAKER_01]: That which pressures you remains, let's say that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I just need to abstain and refrain from overly defining it so to slot and fit what I expect it fitting to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: And just, pretty much out of faith, stick to the right level, because you recognize, well, but hold on, my goal is not to satisfy my intellectual need for clarity and fit, but my goal is to be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I've come halfway up, and there is freedom from suffering to that degree, at that extent, but now I kind of carry on more, to fit it even better, in a satisfactory manner.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, but if I don't do that, I still have nothing to lose.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I don't give in to that pressure, to overly clarify freedom from doubt and this hindrance and that hindrance, but actually just stay with where the pressure is, recognize it to the extent that I'm not pressured towards things that it wants me to go, it's like, yeah, I have nothing to lose there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it's uncomfortable only because of your need to kind of overly do it, overshoot the mark.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's when I was going to ask you, like, what body posture are you now?
[SPEAKER_01]: Sitting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, did you have to stop and think about it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Did you have to get up?
[SPEAKER_01]: You already know that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, sometimes when there is too much of a desire to, like, figure it out and understand, you stop seeing the obvious, that is still there, such as body.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still there, even if you don't explicitly think about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's to learn how to keep seeing it without explicitly thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the body postures that you can contemplate, or the nature of the body, the universal nature of the organs, regardless of the situation, regardless of the emotional and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because those things would set in.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then they become that which your body is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you see it correctly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the body is already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: The whole, the way of attending to this here and now, it's already on the basis of body being in a certain position here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, it cannot be elsewhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's more like you undoing that expectation to find the body only after you think about it on your own terms, because it's already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, I can think about it to find it, or I can refrain from thinking and look, it's already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, that's the direction that everything else goes.
[SPEAKER_01]: First, yeah, you need to pick it up with your craving, to know what to look for.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, if you're doing it rightly, time recognizes, oh, I'll find it by not actually actively engaging with this craving in that direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yeah, pick it up, so I know what to recognize, but recognition is over there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, what I found, one kind of good way of putting it, is what Venerable Aniga wrote in that essay regarding yoniso, manasikāra, is that even the recognition of the body already there, is because the body is already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, if you understand that, then basically... Well, it's it's the question of understanding it once.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a question of training yourself to keep seeing it that way.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, like, let's say, you do, you are able to endure things on the right level, to the extent that the pressure is not felt, at least once or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, is there something else you need to do?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you just need to make sure that you always stay above those pressures, then.
[SPEAKER_02]: But there's not... as in, I don't... there's nothing... there's not really more you need to kind of do on top of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, there is, but that can become only apparent once you're thoroughly above the pressures.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because... but yeah, the suttas do say what you need to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you get established in not being moved by any pressure, when it's completely equanimous,
[SPEAKER_01]: Peaceful, immovable, quite delightful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now you regard that the same way as you did the precious.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, this is also a debt, a boil, a dart, affliction.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm better off even not having this.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then your mind turns away even from that first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's where the whole āsava, all of the āsavas will have to be uprooted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing can remain lingering.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, in order to do that, yeah, first establish yourself in the entire piece, then no hindrance can move you, and then this will kind of...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, I wouldn't say it would come naturally, but with all the suttas that we already know, there is no way that then you would not... Oh, hold on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, this too, actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be better if...
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it would be better if it were not there to begin with, certainly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because any experience that arises is not worth clinging to.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not worth having, it's not worth delighting or finding safety in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even this pure, purified, freed experience from all the pressures, all the compulsions, all the hindrances, all the doubts and everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not mine, not for me, not I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that experience of being free from pressures, hindrances, is real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a phenomenon enduring there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Phenomenon where the directionality of affirming or denying is completely evened out.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's completely even.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no more leaning forward nor against.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's still real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: The middle ground is real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you see it, means, oh, you will know it as impermanent, unownable, rightly developed, but equally not worth owning either.